<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>I'd rather be eating</title><link href="https://mfoos.github.io/blog/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://mfoos.github.io/blog/feeds/all-en.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://mfoos.github.io/blog/</id><updated>2018-02-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>Getting Started with R...maybe</title><link href="https://mfoos.github.io/blog/getting-started-with-rmaybe.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-02-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-02-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Marianna Foos</name></author><id>tag:mfoos.github.io,2018-02-24:/blog/getting-started-with-rmaybe.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am probably the wrong person to write this, but I sent more than one email on the topic, so I have to write a blog post. THEM'S THE RULES.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I got an email saying "I'm new to R, and I just don't know where to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am probably the wrong person to write this, but I sent more than one email on the topic, so I have to write a blog post. THEM'S THE RULES.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few days ago I got an email saying "I'm new to R, and I just don't know where to start learning it, can you help?" (This may seem odd given that I run an R user group, but the sender is not local to the group, she found me because I'm in her state). You might say that there are lots of resources on the web (true), but when you are suffering from "don't know where to start", you... don't know where to start! If you are unfamiliar with this experience, you should see me trying to order takeout when I'm reeeeeeally tired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the reason I feel unfit to write this is that I learned R in an obscenely expensive graduate statistics class. In that class, I learned basic data structures and how to copy code verbatim. To be honest, it took me a long time to stop getting that error you get when you forget the comma when subsetting rows AND columns. Then I landed at an internship that was all R all the time. Which brings me to my advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identify a problem and solve it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
   This is both the best programming-learning advice I've ever gotten, and some of the most frustrating. It's hard to pick something out of thin air, especially if you're so new that you can't tell what's an appropriate problem. Or if you're anxious to LEARN THE IMPORTANT THINGS OMG (I'm here with Python, btw). So I guess I recommend you think about what prompted you to seek out R (cool plots? want to run the same analysis many times with different data?), and draw from that. I also recommend that you not dismiss candidate ideas because they seem too easy. I learned my first programming language writing a script that read a formatted file and did third-grade arithmetic. It was gruesome and you can see it &lt;a href="https://github.com/mfoos/NPLab_Projects/blob/master/winner_finder-3x4x1.plx"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. When you choose a problem to solve, you are keeping your eyes on the prize, so you can focus on learning things that solve your problem/subproblems, and your path is sort of linear toward a goal. It's sort of like how people who are saving money for a concrete goal are often better able to do so than those who are saving for savings' sake. Eventually, you'll probably start to think about adding features or changing how something works, and you can branch out then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read other peoples' code&lt;/strong&gt;
   I think every time I read someone else's R code, I learn about a new function that I hadn't known I didn't know. It will also teach you about the value of liberal whitespace usage. The ideal way to read other peoples' code is to see something cool a coworker has done, and say "cool, how did you do that?" because then it's likely to be a smallish example, about something interesting to you, and hopefully an opportunity for some coaching. If that's not in the cards, you're still sitting pretty, because the recent uptick in popularity of R has been paralleled by interest in reproducible research, so many many many many R resources will contain a link to the code used to generate them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Attend a Data Carpentry workshop or read their materials&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;a href="http://www.datacarpentry.org/"&gt;Data Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; is a non-profit with the mission of teaching computational data skills to researchers, with a strong focus on becoming productive as fast as possible. Workshops happen all over the world, and you can either find one to attend on their website, or encourage your organization to host one. (Usually places host them to educate THEIR people, but sometimes they are open enrollment.) If you can't swing one of those options, all the teaching materials are online, and you can work on them independently. The general R lesson is &lt;a href="http://www.datacarpentry.org/R-ecology-lesson/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Data Carpentry has a sister organization called &lt;a href="https://software-carpentry.org/"&gt;Software Carpentry&lt;/a&gt; that skews more toward software than data, and beyond that, I simply prefer the DC lessons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R User Groups&lt;/strong&gt;
   This won't help everyone, but if you live near a city or large university, there may be an R User Group or &lt;a href="rladies.org"&gt;R-Ladies&lt;/a&gt; chapter near you. If you are a gender minority (female, non-binary, etc.) you can even check out &lt;a href="https://www.r-bloggers.com/introducing-r-ladies-remote-chapter/"&gt;R-Ladies Remote&lt;/a&gt;, which is in the powering-up stage as I write this. User groups usually offer tutorials and seminars, and are an opportunity to meet potential mentors, mentees or collaborators. Plus, it is among the best ways to keep up-to-date with R happenings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thus ends the personal endorsement section&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are some additional resources that get positive reviews from the folks around me&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DataCamp&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;a href="https://www.datacamp.com/"&gt;DataCamp&lt;/a&gt; offers a ton of courses in R and Python, including many taught by "R celebrities" like Julia Silge and Charlotte Wickham (and several R-Ladies founders). Full disclosure, DataCamp sponsored an R-Ladies Boston. I've never used DataCamp, but my R-Ladies members rave about it. As I understand it, some courses are free, and some are subscriber-only, with the first chapter free to view. Pay plans are $25-29 per month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;R4DS&lt;/strong&gt;
   &lt;a href="http://r4ds.had.co.nz/"&gt;R4DS&lt;/a&gt; or "R for Data Science" is a free ebook (or non-free paperback) by Hadley Wickham and Garrett Grolemund, who both work at RStudio and are actually also DataCamp instructors. They thus contribute a lot to shaping the language and have their fingers on the pulse of R. I have landed in this ebook while troubleshooting, but never tried to go through it systematically (some R-Ladies chapters are doing this, I believe)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MOOCs in general&lt;/strong&gt;
   Udemy, Coursera, Udacity and edX all have R courses. I started the JHU Data Science Specialization on Coursera and I wouldn't recommend it for absolute beginners to R. But other than that, I have no experience with R MOOCs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RStudio's Resource list&lt;/strong&gt;
   I only found &lt;a href="https://www.rstudio.com/online-learning/#r-programming"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; researching this blog post. I haven't clicked past the list, but folks at RStudio KNOW R and have a significant interest in getting more people using it. They also make the RStudio IDE and the RMarkdown and Shiny packages, so they are go-tos for those R-adjacent topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Alright, kiddos, go learn some R! Go help someone learn R!&lt;/h4&gt;</content><category term="R"></category><category term="learning"></category></entry><entry><title>Slides from Boston Bioconductor Shiny Talk</title><link href="https://mfoos.github.io/blog/slides-from-boston-bioconductor-shiny-talk.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-12-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Marianna Foos</name></author><id>tag:mfoos.github.io,2017-12-08:/blog/slides-from-boston-bioconductor-shiny-talk.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mfoos.github.io/blog/pdfs/shiny_talk_bostonbioconductor.pdf"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; are my slides from tonight's Shiny talk at Boston Bioconductor. Get at me on Twitter with feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: And &lt;a href="https://github.com/dfjenkins3/shiny_kmeans_tutorial"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the repo for the tutorial by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dfjenkins3"&gt;@dfjenkins3&lt;/a&gt; that preceeded my talk.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://mfoos.github.io/blog/pdfs/shiny_talk_bostonbioconductor.pdf"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; are my slides from tonight's Shiny talk at Boston Bioconductor. Get at me on Twitter with feedback!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: And &lt;a href="https://github.com/dfjenkins3/shiny_kmeans_tutorial"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the repo for the tutorial by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dfjenkins3"&gt;@dfjenkins3&lt;/a&gt; that preceeded my talk.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Shiny"></category><category term="slides"></category><category term="talks"></category></entry><entry><title>Ughhhh, Computer Shopping</title><link href="https://mfoos.github.io/blog/ughhhh-computer-shopping.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-09-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Marianna Foos</name></author><id>tag:mfoos.github.io,2017-09-17:/blog/ughhhh-computer-shopping.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was a lifelong Windows user until 2010 when I was impressed by Ubuntu on my &lt;a href="http://www.dell.com/us/dfh/p/inspiron-mini9/pd"&gt;Dell Mini 9&lt;/a&gt;. Remember netbooks? They were like crappy, expensive, bulky Chromebooks, but they were ahead of their time introducing mainstream users to Ubuntu. When the laptop I bought when I left for college …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was a lifelong Windows user until 2010 when I was impressed by Ubuntu on my &lt;a href="http://www.dell.com/us/dfh/p/inspiron-mini9/pd"&gt;Dell Mini 9&lt;/a&gt;. Remember netbooks? They were like crappy, expensive, bulky Chromebooks, but they were ahead of their time introducing mainstream users to Ubuntu. When the laptop I bought when I left for college died in 2011 after several months of being pink, I bought another PC that turned out to be a spectacular piece of crap. It &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blue_Screen_of_Death"&gt;BSoD&lt;/a&gt;’d several times a day, and was eventually helped to limp along by replacing Windows with CrunchBang Linux. The Linux came in pretty handy for my bioinformatics night school classes, but the computer continued to be difficult. After putting up with my whining for a year or so, my ex sold me his old MacBook Pro for the tidy sum of me throwing my existing computer down a flight of concrete stairs behind our apartment building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked the terminal access, the “just working”, and the wankless access to Microsoft Office, and my bioinformatics professor got a very satisfying “I Told You So” out of it. I am still using that MBP, but the model is no longer supported, and I’m starting to notice performance issues. I’ve been casually window-shopping for a new machine, and it’s got me thinking about what’s out there, option-wise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a good time to plug &lt;a href="https://olgabotvinnik.com/blog/macbook-setup/"&gt;Olga Botvinnik's recent MacBook setup post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know Chromebooks started out as an inexpensive option for web browsing and word processing, but have come up in the world. For those who don’t know, Chromebooks run Chrome OS rather than Windows or OSX. Apps are available from Google and through the Chrome webstore, but &lt;a href="https://sites.google.com/a/chromium.org/dev/chromium-os/chrome-os-systems-supporting-android-apps"&gt;there’s apparently also an android integration in the works, that’s in stable release for some hardware.&lt;/a&gt; Chrome OS is built on top of Linux, but the Linux isn’t intended to be “exposed” to the user, for lack of a better word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve had a Samsung 3 (XE500C13-K02US) &lt;a href="https://www.google.com/chromebook/device/samsung-chromebook-3/"&gt;Chromebook&lt;/a&gt; for about a year, which I bought after reading about &lt;a href="https://github.com/dnschneid/crouton"&gt;crouton&lt;/a&gt;, which is a sort of live-switching dual-boot between Chrome OS and the Linux environment of your choice (I assume there are limitations, but I set up Ubuntu 14.04 (Trusty Tahr) with Unity and never looked back). I think I used a mishmash of tutorials, because none/all look right when I check now. I also definitely read somewhere that you could only use crouton with a Chromebook with an Intel processor, but have not been able to find the reference. I don’t know whether it is true, or was ever true. In any case, that factored into my decision to buy the Samsung 3, which I’m very happy with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that’s what this rambling post was supposed to be about: Options for Chromebook users who use the shell as much as most people use MS Word or Excel. When I buy a computer to “get work done on the run”, that includes parsing text with GNU utilities, Python and R scripting, and communicating with Github for version control and static web publishing, among other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s my list of demands:&lt;br&gt;
- Terminal that works like a linux terminal, including git, ssh, apt-get/yum, curl and GNU text utilities
- &lt;a href="http://jupyter.org/"&gt;Jupyter notebooks&lt;/a&gt; and/or &lt;a href="https://ipython.org/"&gt;ipython&lt;/a&gt;
- &lt;a href="https://www.rstudio.com/products/RStudio/"&gt;RStudio&lt;/a&gt; (tfw you’re a Shiny developer)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as I can tell, there are three options, which are not all mutually exclusive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/dnschneid/crouton"&gt;Crouton&lt;/a&gt; -  Lets you run side-by-side sessions in Chrome OS and a Linux desktop, with instant screen swapping.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Pros:&lt;/strong&gt; You can do whatever you want with the Linux desktop once you’ve set it up.&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cons:&lt;/strong&gt; Fussy to set up, overrides security, results in an opaque warning that could get you in trouble at an airport (it starts beeping if you don’t hit ctrl + D) or get your chroots (basically your configuration) erased by a well meaning friend who needed to check their email (the screen prompts you to “re-enable” the secure mode)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://blog.lessonslearned.org/building-a-more-secure-development-chromebook/"&gt;Google Play / Termux&lt;/a&gt; - aka the &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/kennwhite"&gt;Kenn White&lt;/a&gt; method, using an Android app &lt;a href="https://termux.com/"&gt;(Termux)&lt;/a&gt; that’s a terminal emulator/Linux environment (requires that your Chromebook supports Google Play)&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Pros:&lt;/strong&gt; Runs without root, doesn’t compromise Chrome OS integrity/security&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cons:&lt;/strong&gt; No GUI for RStudio, unclear how hard it’s going to be to install non-standard languages like R, looks sort of fussy to set up (but I haven’t actually tried it yet, and my threshold for fussy has a lot to do with “doesn’t work as promised”), not available to all Chromebook users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rely on remotes - Set up a server elsewhere (like an Amazon EC2 instance) with the software you want to use, and ssh into it from either the native crosh shell, or a supported ssh client from the Chrome app store&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Pros:&lt;/strong&gt; Real Linux (Install anything! No surprises!), RStudio Server and Jupyter mean GUIs are available via the browser, same environment available to multiple devices&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Cons:&lt;/strong&gt; Requires internet connection and additional infrastructure investment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m currently doing #1 and considering switching to a combo of #2 &amp;amp; #3 - I really use RStudio a lot! A couple of people have already written about doing this:&lt;br&gt;
- &lt;a href="http://code.markedmondson.me/rstudio-server-chromebook/"&gt;http://code.markedmondson.me/rstudio-server-chromebook/&lt;/a&gt;
- &lt;a href="https://jrfarrer.github.io/r/2016/12/29/RStudio-Lightsail.html"&gt;https://jrfarrer.github.io/r/2016/12/29/RStudio-Lightsail.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must say, though, that in the process of writing this post, I’ve had a realization about what sort of specs I need on my next “main” computer. I don’t game and I don’t edit images, and the heavier-lifting data stuff I do needs to get off-loaded to a cluster anyway. So I suppose my one, big, remaining question is:  Why do other developers have high-powered MBPs? Not in a “you’re wrong” way - In a “what am I missing?” way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t have comments set up on the blog, but I am quite curious to hear feedback on this! Tweet me at &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MariannaFoos"&gt;@mariannafoos&lt;/a&gt;, or well...figure out my gmail address :)&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="hardware"></category><category term="chromebook"></category></entry><entry><title>How I Do Shiny</title><link href="https://mfoos.github.io/blog/how-i-do-shiny.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-08-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-08-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Marianna Foos</name></author><id>tag:mfoos.github.io,2017-08-09:/blog/how-i-do-shiny.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've had a handful of conversations recently with people learning Shiny who all agree that despite the many available tutorials and examples, sometimes it's hard to figure out how to do what YOU want to do. I think this is exemplified by how long it took me to figure out …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've had a handful of conversations recently with people learning Shiny who all agree that despite the many available tutorials and examples, sometimes it's hard to figure out how to do what YOU want to do. I think this is exemplified by how long it took me to figure out how to read a CSV into a Shiny app as a global object. So here's a collection of my hard-won pro-tips, as well as some non-obvious approaches for "this shouldn't be complicated" tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1. If the "invalidation" (odd-shaped boxes with arrows) explanations don't make sense to you, don't sweat it.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some understanding of how the reactivity works will probably help you in the long right, but don't feel like you need to 110% understand it to get started. Try out the built-in [to RStudio] geyser app, and experiment with changing the inputs and outputs. You can build useful stuff with only that logic. Reactivity boils down to a "downstream flow" - when an input changes, everything that uses it (or uses something that uses it, etc etc) recalculates/rerenders. One thing about this that can be tricky is a situation where you recalculate based on an input, and use another input in some unexciting way like generating a label - they are both equally able to trigger things downstream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2. If there's no output, but no error (and you're not already error-handling it), check your in/out alignment&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish someone had told me this when I was getting started. If you do this in server.R:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;output&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;mytable &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; renderDataTable&lt;span class="p"&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;table_code&lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;but pair it with this in ui.R:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;tableOutput&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;mytable&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;You will pull your hair out looking for the silent bug. I have also often done this by putting &lt;code&gt;renderPlot&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;plotOutput&lt;/code&gt; because DUH, I want it to render in the UI.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;3. Mutable globals exist, they're just different. And you should use them.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can load a csv into a data.frame (and maybe manipulate it) outside the server function and refer to that globally within the server function. You quickly discover, however, that if you want to modify it based on user input, you can no longer just refer to it like a regular R variable. That's because everything inside the server function must be a "reactive" variable (unless it's inside the curly braces of another function). So to limit code duplication, you should consider making a reactive object if you're re-using the modified object. Here's an example from my life:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;my_df &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; read_tsv&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;cats.txt&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
shinyServer&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kr"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;input&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; output&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;

  reactive_df &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; reactive&lt;span class="p"&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;
    my_df &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; my_df &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt; filter&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;cat &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Herbie&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;

  output&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;mytable &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; renderDataTable&lt;span class="p"&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;
    reactive_df&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# you gotta reference it like a function&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;

  output&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;mydownload &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; downloadHandler&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    filename &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Herbie.txt&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    content &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kr"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kp"&gt;file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
      write.table&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;reactive_df&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kp"&gt;file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;4. Use dplyr to subset globals instead of making new reactive objects&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that was handy, right? But maybe you're like me, and you want to show URLs as links in the webapp, but text in the download. &lt;a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/dplyr/index.html"&gt;Dplyr&lt;/a&gt; has been a LIFESAVER for me in this regard. Let me revisit the example above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;reactive_df &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; reactive&lt;span class="p"&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;
  my_df &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; my_df &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt; filter&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;cat &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Herbie&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;})&lt;/span&gt;

output&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;mytable &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; renderDataTable&lt;span class="p"&gt;({&lt;/span&gt;
  reactive_df&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&amp;gt;%&lt;/span&gt; mutate&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;PetfinderURL &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; createLink&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;PetfinderURL&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class="p"&gt;},&lt;/span&gt; escape &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kc"&gt;FALSE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="c1"&gt;# this is so the link will display as a link, not the HTML&lt;/span&gt;

output&lt;span class="o"&gt;$&lt;/span&gt;mydownload &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;-&lt;/span&gt; downloadHandler&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
  filename &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Herbie.txt&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  content &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kr"&gt;function&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="kp"&gt;file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;){&lt;/span&gt;
    write.table&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;reactive_df&lt;span class="p"&gt;(),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kp"&gt;file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;h3&gt;5. Using very long lists for dropdowns&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) I found it difficult to find examples for loading dropdown choices from a file. I am a bioinformatician. It sucked. Short version: ui.R can't access variables from server.R. If you'd like to &lt;code&gt;read_csv()&lt;/code&gt; a file, you have to do it a) in a global.R file if you're doing a "2 file app", or b) outside both server and ui functions if you're doing a "1 file app".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) For most of the apps I write, the &lt;code&gt;selectizeInput()&lt;/code&gt; is populated by gene names. So that's like 30k entries, and although that's a "fast enough" load when you're just starting a data analysis, it's not fast enough for your webapp users. The best solution I've found for this is &lt;code&gt;updateSelectizeInput()&lt;/code&gt;. Two of its parameters are tricky: &lt;em&gt;session&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;server&lt;/em&gt;. For the former, you just need to add "session" as a parameter of the server function: &lt;code&gt;shinyServer(function(input, output, session) {...}&lt;/code&gt; and you're done. For the latter, you have to choose whether to use the server for the &lt;code&gt;update&lt;/code&gt;. Using &lt;code&gt;server = TRUE&lt;/code&gt; is faster, but it triggers a reactive event, so the page in effect loads twice if the page is initialized with a selection (&lt;code&gt;selectizeInput(..., selected = "value")&lt;/code&gt; in ui.R). Nobody seems to be bothered by this but me, so if you know how to get around this, get at me on the twitters. If you use &lt;code&gt;server = FALSE&lt;/code&gt; it's a little slower, but still better than &lt;code&gt;selectizeInput()&lt;/code&gt; and also it behaves like you want it to. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;6. Use sqlite for faster lookup&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, genes: there are a lot of them. Doing a lookup on a data.frame is surprisingly unacceptably slow. This should not be what slows down your app! SQLite aka sqlite3 comes standard with most Linux distros I've used, as well as Mac OSX, and it's basically like awesome csv. Read up on it, and/or use &lt;a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/RSQLite/index.html"&gt;RSQLite&lt;/a&gt; to create and access a database (it can be one table, tbh) and your lookups will be so much faster (at least on the server, ymmmv on a laptop).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;7. Use lists to return multiple values&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This falls under "feels hacky" but if you find yourself writing an ... elaborate &lt;code&gt;reactive()&lt;/code&gt; function, you might want to return multiple values. For me this happened when I wanted to process three dataframes the exact same way and did it in a loop rather than create three independent reactive functions. You can use a list to return multiple values, and just pass the variable around, accessing each variable with &lt;code&gt;secretly_a_list()[[1]]&lt;/code&gt; etc. The truth is, Shiny can basically do anything, if you're willing to get crazy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;8. The syntax for using DT::renderDataTable is &lt;code&gt;output$mydt &amp;lt;- DT::renderDataTable({datatable(dat, args)})&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's basically it. If you google around for "datatable shiny" there are lots of fabulous options you can use, and friggin NONE of them explain the syntax. Boom. Done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Alright, I've spent enough time writing this. PUBLISH!&lt;/h4&gt;</content><category term="R"></category><category term="Shiny"></category><category term="How-To"></category></entry><entry><title>Event Report - DataRescue Boston @MIT</title><link href="https://mfoos.github.io/blog/event-report-datarescue-boston-mit.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-02-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-02-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Marianna Foos</name></author><id>tag:mfoos.github.io,2017-02-23:/blog/event-report-datarescue-boston-mit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time an awesome lady I met on the internet, who blogs about challenging her own comfort zone, asked me if I might ever want to guest post. From what I can tell, she started a company, redirected her efforts there, and is sort of MIA on the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time an awesome lady I met on the internet, who blogs about challenging her own comfort zone, asked me if I might ever want to guest post. From what I can tell, she started a company, redirected her efforts there, and is sort of MIA on the internet now. I hope it's her dream come true. Anyway, I had a hard time coming up with a challenge for my own comfort zone, but had finally settled on "attend a hackathon".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This past Saturday, I attended a hackathon hosted by &lt;a href="https://datarescue-boston.github.io/"&gt;DataRescue Boston&lt;/a&gt; at MIT. DataRescue is a movement of volunteers working to archive taxpayer-funded scientific data in the event that an antagonistic administration were to limit access to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I arrived at MIT half an hour late, because I screwed up, and was relieved to discover that it was still trickle-in time. There was a ton of coffee, bagels/toppings, OJ, fruit salad and awesome vegetarian breakfast burritos from Feed the People. I checked in, got a nametag, sticker and level keychain (!!!!) and was offered the option of opting out of photography at the event. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went and washed the MBTA slime off my hands, and sat down at a round table just as the program began. The organizers introduced themselves and the volunteer guides/managers, the purpose and motivation for Data Rescue, the facility information, the schedule and an outline of the roles folks could choose for the event. Two things that I really liked were the inclusion of facility information (bathroom and info table locations, etc.) and the pre-existing "Attendee Info Packet" they'd set up online with info in greater detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People chose their own "track" from:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surveyors: Researching government departments not already being archived (not touching data)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeders: Use the information supplied by the surveyors to identify and queue data that needs to be archived&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Harvesters: Download data, document download process, and upload to the archive&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storytellers: Document the event for communication to the public and the press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roles/tracks was something I had researched ahead of time, but didn't quite understand, so I want to dwell on them for a moment. First of all, I'm a "technical" person aka I code, but given the importance of the mission, I went with the intention of "going where I was most needed". It turns out that was unnecessary: because of the size and parallelization of the national movement, there is already plenty in all stages of the pipeline. In addition, the software and workflow are designed so that at every stage (2-3 hours) the data is annotated and repackaged for the next person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other thing I noticed about the tracks was that there were WAY more people there to "harvest" than anything else. To me this suggests that, of the people who were aware of the event, the majority of the ones who interpreted it as "for them" were coding people - big surprise. I'm a bit red-faced here because I've always been under the impression that all hackathons say that everyone is welcome regardless of technical skill, but that this is essentially lip service. I was wrong about at least this event and probably in general. Surveying and seeding needed subject matter experts, people familiar with government, and anyone know knows how to gather information on the web. Harvesting needed web-scrapers, sure, but we also needed subject matter experts, and web/UI developers (what just happened?! was it javascript?!). Storytelling needed critical thinkers and policy folks and technical journalists and social media experts and photographers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we had resettled by track, and then again by department (shoutout to team NOAA!) it was about 10am, and I'd say it took me about another hour to familiarize myself with the workflow (how to start, what to check) and choose a dataset that seemed right for me. I was just getting started relearning the Python BeautifulSoup package when many, many pizzas arrived. We all nommed pizza and continued working. Folks were helping each other out, both at the table and between tables via Slack - What does this mean? I'm getting this error, can someone help? Why is it doing this? Did javascript just happen? It was very relaxed and many an "I don't know" was gracefully given and accepted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was plagued by a phantom 404 (after I checked the urls!) which ate up a lot of my time, but I eventually solved it (the library I used to check urls preprocessed them, the library I used to download didn't) and finished my download and archiving at home later. I now have the info and logins to contribute independent of an event, and I hope to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the event a lot - I was worried about disorganization and drudgery, but the DataRescue folks (Boston organizers and above) were very organized, and the distributed pipeline meant that individuals having issues didn't cause problems for the general forward progress of the group. There's another event coming up at &lt;a href="https://datarescue-boston.github.io/northeastern/"&gt;Northeastern&lt;/a&gt;, which I recommend checking out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Random comments on the event: There were gender neutral and accessible bathrooms, as well as vegetarian and gluten-free food options. There was no ASL/captioning, but all of the information was available in static written form. I'd say attendance was at least 1/3 women.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="hackathons"></category></entry><entry><title>Lightning Talks for the Unignited</title><link href="https://mfoos.github.io/blog/lightning-talks-for-the-unignited.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2017-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-01-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Marianna Foos</name></author><id>tag:mfoos.github.io,2017-01-08:/blog/lightning-talks-for-the-unignited.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, while researching this blog post, I learned that there are KINDS of lightning talks. One of them is called "Ignite" so that's the source of the title. As organizer for &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/R-Ladies-Boston/"&gt;R-Ladies Boston&lt;/a&gt;, I'm recruiting for lightning talks for our next meetup. The folks who don't need to be asked …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, while researching this blog post, I learned that there are KINDS of lightning talks. One of them is called "Ignite" so that's the source of the title. As organizer for &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/R-Ladies-Boston/"&gt;R-Ladies Boston&lt;/a&gt;, I'm recruiting for lightning talks for our next meetup. The folks who don't need to be asked twice have already signed up, so now I'm aiming for the second line: folks who are interested/excited/curious about lightning talks but don't see the path to giving one. I know they exist because more often than not, I am one of them. (First piece of advice: You know that thing you joke on twitter about quitting your job to go do full time? Give a talk about that - I did.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these links come from &lt;a href="https://github.com/catehstn/technically-speaking"&gt;the Technically Speaking newsletter&lt;/a&gt;, which I highly recommend. It's run by two women and is about the ups, downs, how-tos, joys and rewards of public speaking. The link goes to back issues on github, but the newsletter itself comes once a week and is the absolute perfect length - I always have time to read the whole thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've pulled out links from 2016 with a focus on lightning talks, inspiration, and the odd bit of talk advice that is equally applicable to short, neighborhood talks as it is to full-length, national ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Why You Should Give A Talk [at R-Ladies Boston this month]&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://artsy.github.io/blog/2016/03/09/public-speaking-part1-is-it-for-me/"&gt;Public Speaking - Part 1: Is it For Me?&lt;/a&gt;
Oooh look! Part of a series! A few thoughts on why public speaking is worth working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://femgineer.com/2016/04/why-you-dont-need-to-be-an-expert-to-speak/"&gt;Why You Don’t Need To Be An Expert To Speak&lt;/a&gt;
Tips on nerves and seeing the interesting topics in your experiences. A good one: ask your peers what they think!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/defensible-me/the-girl-on-the-stage-d5749b97e8be#.5mptfcj2v"&gt;The girl on the stage&lt;/a&gt;
An experienced speaker shares her perspective on the vulnerability we can feel prepping and speaking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Picking A Topic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.heidiwaterhouse.com/2016/06/19/how-to-write-a-lightning-talk/"&gt;How to write a lightning talk&lt;/a&gt;
Favorite part: "I always pick talk topics based on something I’m angry about."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://missgeeky.com/2016/11/21/how-to-brainstorm-talk-ideas/"&gt;How To Brainstorm Talk Ideas&lt;/a&gt;
For those of us who like to be systematic, a framework for identifying topics that inspire you&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/real-solutions-artificial-intelligence/tech-talks-what-to-say-when-you-have-nothing-to-say-4d833f81636c#.oloaz2na0"&gt;Tech Talks: What to Say When You Have “Nothing to Say”&lt;/a&gt;
While very "tech" focused, this includes descriptions of directions you might go in picking a topic, complete with EXAMPLES! ::heart eye emoji::&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://lucybain.com/blog/2016/conference-proposal-ideas/"&gt;How to come up with conference proposal ideas&lt;/a&gt;
Complete with printable worksheet and exertion limit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://cattsmall.com/advice/2016/08/11/become-public-speaker-3.html"&gt;How to become a public speaker in 1 year – Step 3: Generate interesting topics&lt;/a&gt;
Barging in the middle of a series, I know! - I'm a big fan of "find a topic" posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Finer Points&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://scottberkun.com/2009/how-to-give-a-great-ignite-talk/"&gt;How To Give a Great Ignite Talk&lt;/a&gt;
Specific advice for every stage of the lightning talk lifecycle, from brainstorming topics to robust delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://alicebartlett.co.uk/blog/how-to-do-ok-at-slides"&gt;A white-label slide deck&lt;/a&gt;
This post says it's for big audiences, but don't be deterred! It covers a lot "types" of slides, and how to emphasize without clutter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://blog.sqisland.com/2012/06/how-to-be-confident-speaker.html"&gt;How to be a confident speaker&lt;/a&gt;
How to build your confidence by practicing, without taking yourself too seriously&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="resources"></category><category term="speaking"></category><category term="R-Ladies"></category></entry><entry><title>Hello, world!</title><link href="https://mfoos.github.io/blog/hello-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2016-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2016-09-18T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Marianna Foos</name></author><id>tag:mfoos.github.io,2016-09-18:/blog/hello-world.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been on my list of "haunting tasks" (this is a real list I keep) to "make a Jekyll blog on Github pages". However, my experience with Jekyll was: jargon jargon jargon, gem install. Since I try not to type mysterious things into my terminal, I googled around, and eventually …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's been on my list of "haunting tasks" (this is a real list I keep) to "make a Jekyll blog on Github pages". However, my experience with Jekyll was: jargon jargon jargon, gem install. Since I try not to type mysterious things into my terminal, I googled around, and eventually found a page titled &lt;a href="http://guides.rubygems.org/what-is-a-gem/"&gt;"What is a gem?"&lt;/a&gt; that doesn't actually answer the question. Eventually this path led to many complaints about Ruby dependency nightmares with Jekyll, a blog comment about "other static site generators", and my using &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some things I learned while throwing this together today:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am an example-oriented learner, so I briefly browsed the docs and then started with the &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.6.3/quickstart.html"&gt;quickstart&lt;/a&gt; option. It builds you a barebones page that is then as flexible as if built by hand. Viewing config &amp;amp; styling documents is straightforward and you can get on your way fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are using Github pages, the helpful info is in &lt;a href="http://docs.getpelican.com/en/3.6.3/tips.html"&gt;tips&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a static Github page at my .io URL, and I spend a lot of time trying to figure out how I could put a blog at mfoos.github.io/blog/ without having a confusing directory structure and/or files everywhere. I ultimately figured it out using &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io/tutorials/github-pages-blog/"&gt;this Hugo tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.
Basically:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a totally separate repo called "blog" (or whatever)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create a branch called "gh-pages" (this exactly)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WHILE ON THE MASTER BRANCH use &lt;a href="https://github.com/davisp/ghp-import"&gt;ghp-import&lt;/a&gt; to automatically rename the contents of your &lt;code&gt;output&lt;/code&gt; so that ONCE DEPLOYED they all live in the /blog folder &lt;code&gt;git push origin gh-pages&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also noticed that the themes appear slightly different in the local browser preview vs hosted on Github, so make sure you like the hosted version too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I have a blog. Better write about something.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="updates"></category></entry></feed>